Elise Asher
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Elise Asher papers
1923-1994
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Elise Asher
1.6 linear feet
The Elise Asher papers measure 1.6 linear feet and date from 1923 to 1994. The collection includes biographical material, letters, writings, works of art, business records, printed material, and photographs reflecting Asher's career as a poet, painter, and sculptor, and her friendships with many prominent artists of the mid-twentieth century.
Biographical Note
Born in Chicago, Illinois, in 1914, Elise Asher studied at the Art Institute of Chicago, Bradford Junior College, Boston College, and at Simmons College.
She began her career as a poet, culminating in a volume of her poetry entitled The Meandering Absolute. Upon her 1947 arrival in New York City, her attention turned to painting and sculpture. The Tanager Gallery mounted her first solo exhibition in 1953.
Asher was married to painter Nanno de Groot from 1949 to 1957. A year later she married poet Stanley Kunitz, whose work she often illustrated.
Scope and Content Note
The Elise Asher papers, 1923-1994, measure 1.6 linear feet and reflect Asher's career as a poet, painter, and sculptor, and her friendships with many of the more prominent artists of the mid-twentieth century. The collection contains biographical material, letters, writings, works of art, business records, printed material, and photographs.
Notable correspondents found in the collection include Fritz Bultman, Helen Frankenthaler, Philip Guston, Hans Hofmann, Norman Mailer, Robert Motherwell, Louise Nevelson, Mark Rothko, Theodoros Stamos, Jack Tworkov, and Kurt Vonnegut.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series according to material type. The contents of each folder have been arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1923-1976 (box 1, 1 folder)
Series 2: Letters, 1941-1988, undated (box 1, 2 folders)
Series 3: Business Records, 1955-1988, undated (box 1, 43 folders)
Series 4: Writings, 1973-1979, undated (box 1, 4 folders)
Series 5: Artwork, undated (box 1, 2 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1929-1994, undated (boxes 1-3, 30 folders)
Series 7: Photographs, 1951-1973, undated (box 2, 5 folders)
Appendix: Notable Correspondents from Series 2: Letters
Adams, Pat: May 31, 1979
Albert, Calvin: undated Christmas cards (3), one is illustrated
Ashton, Dore: undated postcard?; Jun 12, 1985
Beck, Rosemarie: Jun 1972
Boghosian, Varujan and Marilyn: undated Christmas card
Bourgeois, Louise: Jun 15, 1977
Brooks, Charlotte and Jim: undated letters (2); Apr 3, 1966; Jul 27, 1970; Feb 15, 1971
Brustlein, Daniel: Sep 8, 1955
Bultman, Fritz: undated letters (3); Dec 12, 1964; Jan 2, 1965; Dec 1976
Burlin, Paul and Peggy: Dec 4, 1960
Busa, Peter: Dec 23, 1964
Castellon, Hilda, Paul, and Fred: undated Christmas card
Cavallon, Giorgio: Nov 15, 1955; Sep 8, 1963; Oct 22, 1963; Jan 6, 1965; Oct 3, 1966; Mar 12, 1974
De Kooning, Lisa: 1979 (incomplete letter)
Dorfman, Elsa: undated letter
Ferber, Ilse and Herbert: undated Christmas card; Oct 24, 1960? (with 5 photographs of works)
Ferren, John: undated Christmas card (illustrated); Feb 11, 1964; Jun 30, 1964
Frankenthaler, Helen: undated letters (2); Aug 2, 1956; Jan 19, 1960; Oct 2_, 1960; Apr 1, 1961; Mar 1, 1969; Aug 18, 1969; also see Robert Motherwell
Friedman, Sanford: undated postcard; Jul 7, 1969; Dec 26, 1981; Apr 19, 1988; Dec 27, 1988
Greene, Stephen and Sigrid: undated Christmas cards (2)
Gross, Chaim and Renee: 1967 Christmas card; 1968 Christmas card; 1983 Christmas card
Gruen, John: undated Christmas card
Guston, Philip and Musa: undated Christmas card with illustration; undated letters (3); Jul 29, 1958; Aug 17, 1960; Sep 19, 1963 (illustrated); Jan 10, 1964 (illustrated); Aug 17, 1964 (illustrated); Nov 6, 1964; Sep 22, 1969; Oct 13, 1970; Feb 15, 1971; [1971]; Apr 9, 1971; Aug 2, 1971; Sep 19, 1972; Dec 22, 1972; Jun 12, 1973; Jul 16, 1973 (illustrated); Aug 27, 1974; Dec 1, 1974; Jan 9, 1975; Aug 16, 1979
Hare, David: Mar 7, 1957; Jun 15, 1979; Aug 4, 1980; Jul 14, 1981; Apr 1, 1983
Harmon, Lily: undated Christmas card
Hess, Thomas: undated letters (2); Nov 12, 1974 (envelope only)
Hofmann, Hans and Miz: undated letter; Dec 23, 1952; Dec 1957; Jun 25, 1958; Dec 1, 1958; Jun 3, 1960; Jun 13, 1962; Apr 18, 1963
Kahn, Wolf: Oct 16, 1955
Kootz, Sam and Jane: undated Christmas card
Kuh, Katharine: undated letter; Dec 28, 1974
Mailer, Norman: Apr 11, 1968
Manso?, Leo: Dec 1979 illustrated envelope
Miller, Dorothy: Aug 26, 1953
Morris, Hilda: undated letters (3)
Motherwell, Robert and Renata Ponsold: Mar 3, 1975; Oct 1, 1977; Oct 16, 1978; Feb 25, 1985; Nov 29, 1988; also see Helen Frankenthaler
Nevelson, Louise: Dec 20, 1960 (illustrated card)
O'Doherty, Brian: undated letter; Jul 31, 1967; Aug 5, 1968 Sep 20, 1982
Pavia, Philip: Aug 17, 1982
Reis, Bernard and Becky: undated Christmas cards (2)
Resnick, Milton: Feb 23, 1956
Rosati, James and Carmel: undated Christmas cards (2); also see Art Work
Rothko, Mark: undated letters (2); Jul 20, 1959; Aug 9, 1961; also see Photographs
Stamos, Theodorus: undated letter; Jan 3, 1962; Aug 6, 1964; Jul 14, 1965; Aug 19, 1965; Jul 15, 1966; Jul 19, 1967; Jun 29, 1968; Aug 5, 1968; Jul 23, 1973; Dec 11, 1981
Stevens, May: Jul 14, 1975
Stout, Myron: Mar 25, 1980
Terris, Albert and Virginia: Dec 1953 (illustrated Christmas card)
Tworkov, Jack and family: undated letters (2); Dec 22, 1955 (illustrated Christmas card); Aug 27, 1956; Jul 5, 1960; Dec 11, 1960; Oct 21, 1968; Jan 4, 1983
Varian, Elayne: Oct 6, 1969; Dec 19, 1969
Vonnegut, Kurt: undated letters (2); Jan 29, 1975
Watson, Hildegarde: Feb 24, 1946; Jun 12, 1948; Mar 31, 1951; Jan 27, 1956; Aug 9, 1958
Webb, Nancy: Jan 6, 1986; Dec 15, 1986 (illustrated Christmas card)
Wesley, John: Mar 21, 1987
White, Emil: see Art Work
Williams, William Carlos: Jul 2, 1949 (photocopy); also see Photographs
Wilson, Jane: see John Gruen
Yunkers, Adja: undated cards (2), one illustrated; Feb 3, 1951; Dec 16, 1964
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Names" when they are creators or contributors and under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents.
Subjects:
De Groot, Nanno, 1913-1964; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963
Subjects-Topical:
Women painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Poets -- New York (State) -- New York; Women sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Works of art; Christmas cards; Illustrated letters; Photographs; Slides (photographs)
Names:
Rothko, Mark, 1903-1970; Kunitz, Stanley, 1905-; Bultman, Fritz, 1919-1985; Frankenthaler, Helen, 1928-; Guston, Philip, 1913-; Hofmann, Hans, 1880-1966; Mailer, Norman; Motherwell, Robert; Nevelson, Louise, 1899-1988; Stamos, Theodoros, 1922-; Tworkov, Jack; Vonnegut, Kurt
Provenance
The Elise Asher papers were donated in 1975, 1976, 1989, 1990 and 1995 by the artist.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Microfilmed portion must be consulted on microfilm. Use of unmicrofilmed material requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington D.C. research facility.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is partially available on microfilm reels 4938-4939. The microfilm is available for interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1923-1976, Series 1:; (box 1, 1 folder)
  This series includes a teacher's report, résumés, and an award certificate.
  - Biographical Material, 1923-1976 (Box 1, Reel 4938)
- Letters, 1941-1988, undated, Series 2:; (box 1, 43 folders)
  Letters found here are from Asher's colleagues, including Fritz Bultman, Helen Frankenthaler, Philip Guston, Hans Hofmann, Norman Mailer, Robert Motherwell, Louise Nevelson, Mark Rothko, Theodoros Stamos, Jack Tworkov, and Kurt Vonnegut. The letters primarily concern their art-related activities. A list of notable correspondents can be found in the Appendix.
  - Letters, 1941-1988, undated, (43 folders) (Box 1, Reel 4938)
- Business Records, 1955-1988, undated, Series 3:; (box 1, 2 folders)
  This series consists of miscellaneous loan agreements and receipts.
  - Loan agreements and receipts, 1955-1988, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 4938)
- Writings, 1973-1979, undated, Series 4:; (box 1, 4 folders)
  Writings include poems and artist statements by Asher. Also found here are miscellaneous writings about Asher: Elise Asher at Ingber by Carl Little (undated); Asher's Outscapes at Ingber by Ellen Romano Russotto (undated); Another World: Elise Asher at Ingber Gallery by Ellen Russotto (undated); excerpts of Brian O'Doherty's article, "Elise Asher: Ut Pictura Poesis," Art In America (1973); and Elise Asher at the Ingber Gallery by Jeanne Miles.
  - Poems by Elise Asher, undated (Box 1, Reel 4938)
  - Artist's Statements, 1973-1975, undated (Box 1, Reel 4938)
  - Typescript for Exhibition Catalog The Book As Art by Daniel Fendrick, 1975 (Box 1, Reel 4938)
  - Miscellaneous Writings About Asher, 1973-1979, undated (Box 1, Reel 4938)
- Artwork, undated, Series 5:; (box 1, 2 folders)
  Found here are two collages by James Rosati and a watercolor by Emil White.
  - Collages by James Rosati (2), undated (Box 1, Reel 4938)
  - Watercolor by Emil White, undated (Box 1, Reel 4938)
- Printed Material, 1929-1994, undated, Series 6:; (boxes 1-3, 30 folders)
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, press releases, brochures, programs, a published poem by Stanley Kunitz, and three books.
  - Clippings, 1953-1989, undated, (8 folders) (Box 1, Reel 4938)
  - Clippings, 1988-1992 (Box 3 (pam), Reel unfilmed)
  - Exhibition announcements and catalogs for Asher, 1952-1969, undated, (7 folders) (Box 1, Reel 4938)
  - Exhibition announcements and catalogs for Asher, 1970-1989, (5 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4938)
  - Exhibition announcements and catalogs, 1979-1992, undated (Box 3 (pam), Reel unfilmed)
  - Exhibition catalog and price list for Nanno de Groot, 1982 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4938)
  - Press releases, 1976-1986 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4939)
  - Brochures, 1950-1976 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4939)
  - Puppet show programs, 1929-1930 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4939)
  - Book, The Meandering Absolute by Elise Asher, 1955 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4939)
  - Books, This Book Is A Movie edited by Jerry Bowles and Tony Russell, and The Provincetown Artists Cookbook by Christopher Busa, 1971, 1988 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4939)
  - Book, The Visionary Gleam by Elise Asher, 1994 (Box 3 (pam), Reel unfilmed)
  - Published poem The Long Boat by Stanley Kunitz, circa 1987 (Box 1, Reel 4939)
- Photographs, 1951-1973, undated, Series 7:; (box 2, 5 folders)
  Photographs consist of six images of Asher, including one each with Mark Rothko (undated) and William Carlos Williams (1951), and one taken by Hans Namuth. There are also photographs of art works, and photographs of an exhibition installation.
  - Photographs of Elise Asher (6), 1951-1972 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4939)
  - Photographs of works of art, 1971-1973, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4939)
  - Photographs of exhibition installation at The Contemporaries Gallery, 1966 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4939)